Finding Aid for Geddes and Randall Family Papers 1835-1909
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Geddes and Randall Family Papers 1835-1909
Geddes family.
3 oversize volumes
1 linear foot
The Geddes and Randall Family papers record early life in the Ann Arbor, Michigan area. The papers include financial records of paper and sawmills, pioneer reminiscences, personal photographs, and genealogical materials.
02155 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were given to the archives through the family (Donor 9226 ).
The collection is open for research.
The Geddes Family were early pioneers in the Ann Arbor, Michigan area. John Geddes (1801-1889) and his brother Robert Geddes (1797-1866) came to Ann Arbor from Pennsylvania in July 1824. They returned the following year to settle permanently. Robert Geddes constructed a sawmill along the Huron River. While Robert was mainly a farmer, John worked at the mill throughout his lifetime. "Uncle John" was actively involved in early Ann Arbor life and was known for recalling area history. He was also politically active; John was the supervisor of Ann Arbor Township, a Justice of the Peace, and was elected to the state legislature in 1840.
John Geddes's daughter, Sarah, married millwright William T. Randall. He worked for various local mills although spent most of his career as superintendent of the Rock River Paper Company of Marshall, Michigan. He later worked in Beloit, Wisconsin.
The Geddes and Randall Family Papers are subdivided into two series, one for each family. John Geddes papers include reminiscences of his coming to Michigan and his settlement in Ann Arbor. There are also financial records of the sawmill and a journal of daily happenings, 1845-1889, also containing genealogical information. The Randall family papers include correspondence, financial papers and brief diary entries of William Randall; and photograph albums of Sarah Randall.
Subjects:
Geddes family.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Diaries.; Geddes, John.; Millwrights--Michigan.; Randall, William T.; Randall family.; Sawmills--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Geddes family.; Geddes Mill.; Geddes (Mich.); Military uniforms--American.; Mills--Michigan.; Randall family.
Contributors:
Randall, Sarah Geddes.
Genre/Form:
Albums.; Photographs.
- John Geddes Papers
  The Geddes Family Series contains records created by John Geddes. The folder of reminiscences describes his initial voyage to Michigan in 1824 and his stay in Woodruff Grove and Ypsilanti. He also elaborates on his early days in Ann Arbor. The financial papers record prices for basic goods and accounts with local settlers. The ledger/scrapbook was originally an account record during the early 1850s. It was subsequently used as a scrapbook, possibly by one of John Geddes's daughters, by pasting clippings over the journal entries. The account and expense books detail Geddes's personal expenses as well as the sawmill's finances. Both also contain genealogical records of the Geddes family in the front and back covers. John Geddes's "Waste Book" is a journal of daily happenings recorded throughout his life. In it Geddes describes his activities, the weather, community events, work, his surroundings, his relationships, and family vital statistics. It also contains extensive early Ann Arbor genealogical information. Geddes recorded important events in the Geddes family from 1637 to 1889, Ann Arbor births from 1793 to 1889, marriages from 1845 to 1877, and deaths from 1845 to 1889.
  - Pioneer Reminiscences undated (Box 1)
  - Financial Papers 1845-1879 (Box 1)
  - Ledger/Scrapbook 1851- circa 1870 (Box 1)
  - Account Book 1835-1875 (Volume 1)
  - Expenses, Personal and Professional 1835-1889 (Volume 2)
  - "Waste Book" Diary, 1845-1889 (Volume 3)
- Randall Family Papers
  The Randall Family series contains papers mainly created and collected by William T. Randall. Sarah, Gertrude, and J.G. Randall are also represented in the documents. The correspondence files are a mixture of personal family matters and William Randall's professional correspondence. Letters between Sarah Randall, William Randall, and other relatives document their family life. John Geddes writes about personal and professional issues. Business correspondence to and from William Randall and his colleagues, namely J.M. Cobb, document his work at the paper mills. Letters in the 1877 folder describe a death at the Rock River Paper Company. Correspondence in the last folder describes the Geddes farm and land sales. The rest of the financial materials contain various statements, deeds, and receipts for the Rock River Paper Company and assorted personal items. Also included are J.G. Randall's American Medical Association membership certificates. Gertrude Randall's autograph album contains family signatures and messages. Sarah Randall's photograph albums contain family portraits and a few snapshots of paper mills. The 1863 album is almost entirely unlabeled. The following people and places are identified in the 1871 photo album: Charlotte Randall, Herbert Bishop, John Randall, Earle Randall, Julia Randall, Jane Geddes Barnes, Lambert Barnes, Rachel Geddes, Ida Rash, Ella Rash, Julette (or Juliettte) Geddes, E.M. DeForest, Gertrude Randall, Rock River Paper Company in Beloit, Wisconsin, and Geddes Plaster Mill in Geddes, Michigan.
  - Correspondence
    - 1870-1871 (Box 1)
    - 1872 (Box 1)
    - 1873-1874 (Box 1)
    - 1875-1876 (Box 1)
    - 1877 (Box 1)
    - 1878-1879 (Box 1)
    - 1880 (Box 1)
    - 1881-1895 (Box 1)
    - undated (Box 1)
  - William Randall Financial Papers
    - 1864-1875 (Box 1)
    - 1876-1892 (Box 1)
  - William Randall Ledger 1869 (Box 1)
  - William Randall Planners 1872-1874, 1822-1883 (Box 1)
  - J.G. Randall Medical Certificates 1906, 1909 (Box 1)
  - Sarah Randall Photograph Albums
    - 1863 (Box 1)
    - 1871 (Box 1)
  - Gertrude Randall Autograph Album, 1889 (Box 1)
  - Photograph of John Geddes (Box 1)
  - Book inscribed by Henry Savage (Box 1)
    (John Geddes's father-in-law)